we want to take this existing code
and repeat its functionality until the
user
presses q to quit the program
so running our code as it is
the user is prompted to input how many
lines they want the program to output
and this number must be greater than or
equal to three
so we'll input five
the string is printed five times and
then the program ends
what we want the program to do now is
after printing the lines
to again prompt the user how many output
lines do you want
and just repeat this process when the
user enters q
then we want the process to end
and we can achieve this by nesting these
existing loops
in an outer loop
so we'll take the existing code and
place it in a loop now
with our prompt we need to tell the user
that they can press q to quit
so we're still requiring the number to
be greater than or equal to three
and in parentheses we'll display q
to quit currently we're storing the user
input in a local variable called number
of lines
so how should we handle this when we're
not sure whether the user input
is the number of lines or a queue and
the user wants to quit
before we do anything let's first
examine whether the user input queue
so we can initialize a second local
variable
here input string
and this is where we'll capture the
user's initial input
in this case we'll call the down case
method on the user input so that we
don't have to guess whether the user
would input
an uppercase or lowercase q
now we want to break out of our loop if
that input string is equal to q
and again we're just comparing it to the
lowercase q
because we've called down case on that
input
so let's run our code as it is just
examining its behavior if we input a
queue
so i'm going to actually comment out the
code right now
dealing with the number of lines local
variable
we just have our two loops and we're
checking
on how our program will react if we
input a queue
[Music]
so we see the appropriate prompt and
i'll enter a queue this output might be
confusing
because in our code we said we wanted to
break out of the loop
if our input string was equal to q what
we have right now
is actually an infinite loop so i'll hit
ctrl c to break out of that
loop and let's look at our code again
we do have a break statement on line 8
telling our program to break out of this
loop if our input string is equal to q
however this loop is within an outer
loop
and when we use break it only breaks out
of that current inner loop
it's not going to break out of that
outer loop as well
so for this simple problem we're
actually going to duplicate this code
we're going to also break out of our
outer loop if
the input string is equal to q we
initialize
input string on line 7 so before we can
run this code without error
we need to look at the scope in which
that was initialized
the block associated with our inner loop
is nested
inside of the block associated with our
outer loop
line 15 is actually an outer scope from
where
input string was initialized so in order
to access
input string
we'll initialize it at the top of our
outer loop and
now we can access it within our outer
loop and our inner loop
on line 9 will reassign input string
from nil
to the user input
finally let's run our code and see if
it's behaving as we expect when we input
a queue
[Music]
this time i'll input an uppercase q
and you can see that we're not prompted
again we successfully
exited out of both loops and our program
ended
now let's see if we can get the rest of
our code going
we need to change what we assign number
of lines to on line 12.
initially we stored our user input in
number of lines right away
however now we're storing that user
input in the local variable
input string we can actually set number
of lines to reference
input string converted to an integer
so we'll call the string2i method on
that input string
if we reach line 12 of this inner loop
then we already know that the input
string was not equal to q
so we're going to move ahead with
printing out the number of lines
[Music]
again if the number of lines is not
greater than or equal to 3
will display an error message to the
user and repeat this loop
at that point they can enter a different
number or they can choose to quit
if the number of lines is valid we'll
break out of this inner loop
and we want to print the string launch
school is the best
number of lines times so at this
point we expect our code to have all the
functionality that we see
in the example run shown in this problem
i'll enter a number of lines i want the
program to print
and we see it prints the appropriate
number of lines and then prompts me
again
so that's what i want to see this time
i'll enter
an invalid number less than three
[Music]
and i see the error message that's not
enough lines and i'm prompted again
[Music]
and this loop just continues so finally
let me input a queue
to quit the program
and we break out of our loop and we have
exited the program